<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="cfr.xsl"?>
<CFRGRANULE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="CFRMergedXML.xsd">
  <FDSYS>
    <CFRTITLE>45</CFRTITLE>
    <CFRTITLETEXT>Public Welfare</CFRTITLETEXT>
    <VOL>1</VOL>
    <DATE>2005-10-01</DATE>
    <ORIGINALDATE>2005-10-01</ORIGINALDATE>
    <COVERONLY>false</COVERONLY>
    <TITLE>PROTECTION OF HUMAN SUBJECTS</TITLE>
    <GRANULENUM>46</GRANULENUM>
    <HEADING>PART 46</HEADING>
    <ANCESTORS>
      <PARENT HEADING="Title 45" SEQ="2">Public Welfare</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="SUBTITLE A" SEQ="1">DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES</PARENT>
      <PARENT HEADING="SUBCHAPTER A" SEQ="0">GENERAL ADMINISTRATION</PARENT>
    </ANCESTORS>
  </FDSYS>
  <PART>
    <EAR>Pt. 46</EAR>
    <HD SOURCE="HED">PART 46—PROTECTION OF HUMAN SUBJECTS</HD>
    <CONTENTS>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—Basic HHS Policy for Protection of Human Research Subjects</HD>
        <SECHD>Sec.</SECHD>
        <SECTNO>46.101</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what does this policy apply?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.102</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Assuring compliance with this policy—research conducted or supported by any Federal Department or Agency.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.104-46.106</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.107</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB membership.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB functions and operations.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.109</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB review of research.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.110</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Expedited review procedures for certain kinds of research involving no more than minimal risk, and for minor changes in approved research.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.111</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Criteria for IRB approval of research.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.112</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Review by institution.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.113</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Suspension or termination of IRB approval of research.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.114</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cooperative research.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.115</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB records.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.116</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements for informed consent.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.117</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Documentation of informed consent.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.118</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applications and proposals lacking definite plans for involvement of human subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.119</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research undertaken without the intention of involving human subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.120</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Evaluation and disposition of applications and proposals for research to be conducted or supported by a Federal Department or Agency.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.121</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>[Reserved]</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.122</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of Federal funds.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.123</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Early termination of research support: Evaluation of applications and proposals.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.124</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Conditions.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—Additional Protections for Pregnant Women, Human Fetuses and Neonates Involved in Research</HD>
        <SECTNO>46.201</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what do these regulations apply?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.202</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.203</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Duties of IRBs in connection with research involving pregnant women, fetuses, and neonates.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.204</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving pregnant women or fetuses.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.205</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving neonates.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.206</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving, after delivery, the placenta, the dead fetus or fetal material.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.207</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not otherwise approvable which presents an opportunity to understand, prevent, or alleviate a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of pregnant women, fetuses, or neonates.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Additional Protections Pertaining to Biomedical and Behavioral Research Involving Prisoners as Subjects</HD>
        <SECTNO>46.301</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.302</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Purpose.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.303</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.304</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Composition of Institutional Review Boards where prisoners are involved.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.305</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional duties of the Institutional Review Boards where prisoners are involved.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.306</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Permitted research involving prisoners.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
      <SUBPART>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart D—Additional Protections for Children Involved as Subjects in Research</HD>
        <SECTNO>46.401</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what do these regulations apply?</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.402</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.403</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB duties.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.404</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not involving greater than minimal risk.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.405</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving greater than minimal risk but presenting the prospect of direct benefit to the individual subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.406</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving greater than minimal risk and no prospect of direct benefit to individual subjects, but likely to yield generalizable knowledge about the subject's disorder or condition.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.407</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not otherwise approvable which presents an opportunity to understand, prevent, or alleviate a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of children.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.408</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Requirements for permission by parents or guardians and for assent by children.</SUBJECT>
        <SECTNO>46.409</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Wards.</SUBJECT>
      </SUBPART>
    </CONTENTS>
    <AUTH>
      <PRTPAGE P="116"/>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
      <P>5 U.S.C. 301; 42 U.S.C. 289(a).</P>
    </AUTH>
    <EDNOTE>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Editorial Note:</HD>
      <P>The Department of Health and Human Services issued a notice of waiver regarding the requirements set forth in part 46, relating to protection of human subjects, as they pertain to demonstration projects, approved under section 1115 of the Social Security Act, which test the use of cost—sharing, such as deductibles, copayment and coinsurance, in the Medicaid program. For further information see 47 FR 9208, Mar. 4, 1982.</P>
    </EDNOTE>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart A—Basic HHS Policy for Protection of Human Research Subjects</HD>
      <AUTH>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Authority:</HD>
        <P>5 U.S.C. 301; 42 U.S.C. 289, 42 U.S.C. 300v-1(b).</P>
      </AUTH>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.101</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what does this policy apply?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Except as provided in paragraph (b) of this section, this policy applies to all research involving human subjects conducted, supported or otherwise subject to regulation by any federal department or agency which takes appropriate administrative action to make the policy applicable to such research. This includes research conducted by federal civilian employees or military personnel, except that each department or agency head may adopt such procedural modifications as may be appropriate from an administrative standpoint. It also includes research conducted, supported, or otherwise subject to regulation by the federal government outside the United States.</P>
        <P>(1) Research that is conducted or supported by a federal department or agency, whether or not it is regulated as defined in § 46.102(e), must comply with all sections of this policy.</P>
        <P>(2) Research that is neither conducted nor supported by a federal department or agency but is subject to regulation as defined in § 46.102(e) must be reviewed and approved, in compliance with § 46.101, § 46.102, and § 46.107 through § 46.117 of this policy, by an institutional review board (IRB) that operates in accordance with the pertinent requirements of this policy.</P>
        <P>(b) Unless otherwise required by department or agency heads, research activities in which the only involvement of human subjects will be in one or more of the following categories are exempt from this policy:</P>
        <P>(1) Research conducted in established or commonly accepted educational settings, involving normal educational practices, such as (i) research on regular and special education instructional strategies, or (ii) research on the effectiveness of or the comparison among instructional techniques, curricula, or classroom management methods.</P>
        <P>(2) Research involving the use of educational tests (cognitive, diagnostic, aptitude, achievement), survey procedures, interview procedures or observation of public behavior, unless:</P>
        <P>(i) Information obtained is recorded in such a manner that human subjects can be identified, directly or through identifiers linked to the subjects; and (ii) any disclosure of the human subjects' responses outside the research could reasonably place the subjects at risk of criminal or civil liability or be damaging to the subjects' financial standing, employability, or reputation.</P>
        <P>(3) Research involving the use of educational tests (cognitive, diagnostic, aptitude, achievement), survey procedures, interview procedures, or observation of public behavior that is not exempt under paragraph (b)(2) of this section, if:</P>
        <P>(i) The human subjects are elected or appointed public officials or candidates for public office; or (ii) federal statute(s) require(s) without exception that the confidentiality of the personally identifiable information will be maintained throughout the research and thereafter.</P>
        <P>(4) Research, involving the collection or study of existing data, documents, records, pathological specimens, or diagnostic specimens, if these sources are publicly available or if the information is recorded by the investigator in such a manner that subjects cannot be identified, directly or through identifiers linked to the subjects.</P>

        <P>(5) Research and demonstration projects which are conducted by or subject to the approval of department or agency heads, and which are designed to study, evaluate, or otherwise examine:<PRTPAGE P="117"/>
        </P>
        <P>(i) Public benefit or service programs; (ii) procedures for obtaining benefits or services under those programs; (iii) possible changes in or alternatives to those programs or procedures; or (iv) possible changes in methods or levels of payment for benefits or services under those programs.</P>
        <P>(6) Taste and food quality evaluation and consumer acceptance studies, (i) if wholesome foods without additives are consumed or (ii) if a food is consumed that contains a food ingredient at or below the level and for a use found to be safe, or agricultural chemical or environmental contaminant at or below the level found to be safe, by the Food and Drug Administration or approved by the Environmental Protection Agency or the Food Safety and Inspection Service of the U.S. Department of Agriculture.</P>
        <P>(c) Department or agency heads retain final judgment as to whether a particular activity is covered by this policy.</P>
        <P>(d) Department or agency heads may require that specific research activities or classes of research activities conducted, supported, or otherwise subject to regulation by the department or agency but not otherwise covered by this policy, comply with some or all of the requirements of this policy.</P>
        <P>(e) Compliance with this policy requires compliance with pertinent federal laws or regulations which provide additional protections for human subjects.</P>
        <P>(f) This policy does not affect any state or local laws or regulations which may otherwise be applicable and which provide additional protections for human subjects.</P>
        <P>(g) This policy does not affect any foreign laws or regulations which may otherwise be applicable and which provide additional protections to human subjects of research.</P>

        <P>(h) When research covered by this policy takes place in foreign countries, procedures normally followed in the foreign countries to protect human subjects may differ from those set forth in this policy. [An example is a foreign institution which complies with guidelines consistent with the World Medical Assembly Declaration (Declaration of Helsinki amended 1989) issued either by sovereign states or by an organization whose function for the protection of human research subjects is internationally recognized.] In these circumstances, if a department or agency head determines that the procedures prescribed by the institution afford protections that are at least equivalent to those provided in this policy, the department or agency head may approve the substitution of the foreign procedures in lieu of the procedural requirements provided in this policy. Except when otherwise required by statute, Executive Order, or the department or agency head, notices of these actions as they occur will be published in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> or will be otherwise published as provided in department or agency procedures.</P>

        <P>(i) Unless otherwise required by law, department or agency heads may waive the applicability of some or all of the provisions of this policy to specific research activities or classes of research activities otherwise covered by this policy. Except when otherwise required by statute or Executive Order, the department or agency head shall forward advance notices of these actions to the Office for Human Research Protections, Department of Health and Human Services (HHS), or any successor office, and shall also publish them in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> or in such other manner as provided in department or agency procedures.<SU>1</SU>
          <FTREF/>
        </P>
        <FTNT>
          <P>
            <SU>1</SU> Institutions with HHS-approved assurances on file will abide by provisions of title 45 CFR part 46 subparts A-D. Some of the other Departments and Agencies have incorporated all provisions of title 45 CFR part 46 into their policies and procedures as well. However, the exemptions at 45 CFR 46.101(b) do not apply to research involving prisoners, subpart C. The exemption at 45 CFR 46.101(b)(2), for research involving survey or interview procedures or observation of public behavior, does not apply to research with children, subpart D, except for research involving observations of public behavior when the investigator(s) do not participate in the activities being observed.</P>
        </FTNT>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991; 56 FR 29756, June 28, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="118"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.102</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Department or agency head</E> means the head of any federal department or agency and any other officer or employee of any department or agency to whom authority has been delegated.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Institution</E> means any public or private entity or agency (including federal, state, and other agencies).</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Legally authorized representative</E> means an individual or judicial or other body authorized under applicable law to consent on behalf of a prospective subject to the subject's participation in the procedure(s) involved in the research.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Research</E> means a systematic investigation, including research development, testing and evaluation, designed to develop or contribute to generalizable knowledge. Activities which meet this definition constitute research for purposes of this policy, whether or not they are conducted or supported under a program which is considered research for other purposes. For example, some demonstration and service programs may include research activities.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Research subject to regulation,</E> and similar terms are intended to encompass those research activities for which a federal department or agency has specific responsibility for regulating as a research activity, (for example, Investigational New Drug requirements administered by the Food and Drug Administration). It does not include research activities which are incidentally regulated by a federal department or agency solely as part of the department's or agency's broader responsibility to regulate certain types of activities whether research or non-research in nature (for example, Wage and Hour requirements administered by the Department of Labor).</P>
        <P>(f) <E T="03">Human subject</E> means a living individual about whom an investigator (whether professional or student) conducting research obtains</P>
        <P>(1) Data through intervention or interaction with the individual, or</P>
        <P>(2) Identifiable private information.</P>
        <FP>
          <E T="03">Intervention</E> includes both physical procedures by which data are gathered (for example, venipuncture) and manipulations of the subject or the subject's environment that are performed for research purposes. Interaction includes communication or interpersonal contact between investigator and subject. <E T="03">Private information</E> includes information about behavior that occurs in a context in which an individual can reasonably expect that no observation or recording is taking place, and information which has been provided for specific purposes by an individual and which the individual can reasonably expect will not be made public (for example, a medical record). Private information must be individually identifiable (i.e., the identity of the subject is or may readily be ascertained by the investigator or associated with the information) in order for obtaining the information to constitute research involving human subjects.</FP>
        <P>(g) <E T="03">IRB</E> means an institutional review board established in accord with and for the purposes expressed in this policy.</P>
        <P>(h) <E T="03">IRB approval</E> means the determination of the IRB that the research has been reviewed and may be conducted at an institution within the constraints set forth by the IRB and by other institutional and federal requirements.</P>
        <P>(i) <E T="03">Minimal risk</E> means that the probability and magnitude of harm or discomfort anticipated in the research are not greater in and of themselves than those ordinarily encountered in daily life or during the performance of routine physical or psychological examinations or tests.</P>
        <P>(j) <E T="03">Certification</E> means the official notification by the institution to the supporting department or agency, in accordance with the requirements of this policy, that a research project or activity involving human subjects has been reviewed and approved by an IRB in accordance with an approved assurance.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.103</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Assuring compliance with this policy—research conducted or supported by any Federal Department or Agency.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) Each institution engaged in research which is covered by this policy and which is conducted or supported by a federal department or agency shall provide written assurance satisfactory to the department or agency head that it will comply with the requirements <PRTPAGE P="119"/>set forth in this policy. In lieu of requiring submission of an assurance, individual department or agency heads shall accept the existence of a current assurance, appropriate for the research in question, on file with the Office for Human Research Protections, HHS, or any successor office, and approved for federalwide use by that office. When the existence of an HHS-approved assurance is accepted in lieu of requiring submission of an assurance, reports (except certification) required by this policy to be made to department and agency heads shall also be made to the Office for Human Research Protections, HHS, or any successor office.</P>
        <P>(b) Departments and agencies will conduct or support research covered by this policy only if the institution has an assurance approved as provided in this section, and only if the institution has certified to the department or agency head that the research has been reviewed and approved by an IRB provided for in the assurance, and will be subject to continuing review by the IRB. Assurances applicable to federally supported or conducted research shall at a minimum include:</P>
        <P>(1) A statement of principles governing the institution in the discharge of its responsibilities for protecting the rights and welfare of human subjects of research conducted at or sponsored by the institution, regardless of whether the research is subject to federal regulation. This may include an appropriate existing code, declaration, or statement of ethical principles, or a statement formulated by the institution itself. This requirement does not preempt provisions of this policy applicable to department- or agency-supported or regulated research and need not be applicable to any research exempted or waived under § 46.101 (b) or (i).</P>
        <P>(2) Designation of one or more IRBs established in accordance with the requirements of this policy, and for which provisions are made for meeting space and sufficient staff to support the IRB's review and recordkeeping duties.</P>
        <P>(3) A list of IRB members identified by name; earned degrees; representative capacity; indications of experience such as board certifications, licenses, etc., sufficient to describe each member's chief anticipated contributions to IRB deliberations; and any employment or other relationship between each member and the institution; for example: full-time employee, part-time employee, member of governing panel or board, stockholder, paid or unpaid consultant. Changes in IRB membership shall be reported to the department or agency head, unless in accord with § 46.103(a) of this policy, the existence of an HHS-approved assurance is accepted. In this case, change in IRB membership shall be reported to the Office for Human Research Protections, HHS, or any successor office.</P>
        <P>(4) Written procedures which the IRB will follow (i) for conducting its initial and continuing review of research and for reporting its findings and actions to the investigator and the institution; (ii) for determining which projects require review more often than annually and which projects need verification from sources other than the investigators that no material changes have occurred since previous IRB review; and (iii) for ensuring prompt reporting to the IRB of proposed changes in a research activity, and for ensuring that such changes in approved research, during the period for which IRB approval has already been given, may not be initiated without IRB review and approval except when necessary to eliminate apparent immediate hazards to the subject.</P>
        <P>(5) Written procedures for ensuring prompt reporting to the IRB, appropriate institutional officials, and the department or agency head of (i) any unanticipated problems involving risks to subjects or others or any serious or continuing noncompliance with this policy or the requirements or determinations of the IRB and (ii) any suspension or termination of IRB approval.</P>
        <P>(c) The assurance shall be executed by an individual authorized to act for the institution and to assume on behalf of the institution the obligations imposed by this policy and shall be filed in such form and manner as the department or agency head prescribes.</P>

        <P>(d) The department or agency head will evaluate all assurances submitted in accordance with this policy through <PRTPAGE P="120"/>such officers and employees of the department or agency and such experts or consultants engaged for this purpose as the department or agency head determines to be appropriate. The department or agency head's evaluation will take into consideration the adequacy of the proposed IRB in light of the anticipated scope of the institution's research activities and the types of subject populations likely to be involved, the appropriateness of the proposed initial and continuing review procedures in light of the probable risks, and the size and complexity of the institution.</P>
        <P>(e) On the basis of this evaluation, the department or agency head may approve or disapprove the assurance, or enter into negotiations to develop an approvable one. The department or agency head may limit the period during which any particular approved assurance or class of approved assurances shall remain effective or otherwise condition or restrict approval.</P>
        <P>(f) Certification is required when the research is supported by a federal department or agency and not otherwise exempted or waived under § 46.101 (b) or (i). An institution with an approved assurance shall certify that each application or proposal for research covered by the assurance and by § 46.103 of this Policy has been reviewed and approved by the IRB. Such certification must be submitted with the application or proposal or by such later date as may be prescribed by the department or agency to which the application or proposal is submitted. Under no condition shall research covered by § 46.103 of the Policy be supported prior to receipt of the certification that the research has been reviewed and approved by the IRB. Institutions without an approved assurance covering the research shall certify within 30 days after receipt of a request for such a certification from the department or agency, that the application or proposal has been approved by the IRB. If the certification is not submitted within these time limits, the application or proposal may be returned to the institution.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991; 56 FR 29756, June 28, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§§ 46.104—46.106</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.107</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB membership.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Each IRB shall have at least five members, with varying backgrounds to promote complete and adequate review of research activities commonly conducted by the institution. The IRB shall be sufficiently qualified through the experience and expertise of its members, and the diversity of the members, including consideration of race, gender, and cultural backgrounds and sensitivity to such issues as community attitudes, to promote respect for its advice and counsel in safeguarding the rights and welfare of human subjects. In addition to possessing the professional competence necessary to review specific research activities, the IRB shall be able to ascertain the acceptability of proposed research in terms of institutional commitments and regulations, applicable law, and standards of professional conduct and practice. The IRB shall therefore include persons knowledgeable in these areas. If an IRB regularly reviews research that involves a vulnerable category of subjects, such as children, prisoners, pregnant women, or handicapped or mentally disabled persons, consideration shall be given to the inclusion of one or more individuals who are knowledgeable about and experienced in working with these subjects.</P>
        <P>(b) Every nondiscriminatory effort will be made to ensure that no IRB consists entirely of men or entirely of women, including the institution's consideration of qualified persons of both sexes, so long as no selection is made to the IRB on the basis of gender. No IRB may consist entirely of members of one profession.</P>
        <P>(c) Each IRB shall include at least one member whose primary concerns are in scientific areas and at least one member whose primary concerns are in nonscientific areas.</P>
        <P>(d) Each IRB shall include at least one member who is not otherwise affiliated with the institution and who is not part of the immediate family of a person who is affiliated with the institution.</P>

        <P>(e) No IRB may have a member participate in the IRB's initial or continuing review of any project in which <PRTPAGE P="121"/>the member has a conflicting interest, except to provide information requested by the IRB.</P>
        <P>(f) An IRB may, in its discretion, invite individuals with competence in special areas to assist in the review of issues which require expertise beyond or in addition to that available on the IRB. These individuals may not vote with the IRB.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.108</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB functions and operations.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In order to fulfill the requirements of this policy each IRB shall:</P>
        <P>(a) Follow written procedures in the same detail as described in § 46.103(b)(4) and, to the extent required by, § 46.103(b)(5).</P>
        <P>(b) Except when an expedited review procedure is used (see § 46.110), review proposed research at convened meetings at which a majority of the members of the IRB are present, including at least one member whose primary concerns are in nonscientific areas. In order for the research to be approved, it shall receive the approval of a majority of those members present at the meeting.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.109</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB review of research.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) An IRB shall review and have authority to approve, require modifications in (to secure approval), or disapprove all research activities covered by this policy.</P>
        <P>(b) An IRB shall require that information given to subjects as part of informed consent is in accordance with § 46.116. The IRB may require that information, in addition to that specifically mentioned in § 46.116, be given to the subjects when in the IRB's judgment the information would meaningfully add to the protection of the rights and welfare of subjects.</P>
        <P>(c) An IRB shall require documentation of informed consent or may waive documentation in accordance with § 46.117.</P>
        <P>(d) An IRB shall notify investigators and the institution in writing of its decision to approve or disapprove the proposed research activity, or of modifications required to secure IRB approval of the research activity. If the IRB decides to disapprove a research activity, it shall include in its written notification a statement of the reasons for its decision and give the investigator an opportunity to respond in person or in writing.</P>
        <P>(e) An IRB shall conduct continuing review of research covered by this policy at intervals appropriate to the degree of risk, but not less than once per year, and shall have authority to observe or have a third party observe the consent process and the research.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.110</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Expedited review procedures for certain kinds of research involving no more than minimal risk, and for minor changes in approved research.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) The Secretary, HHS, has established, and published as a Notice in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> a list of categories of research that may be reviewed by the IRB through an expedited review procedure. The list will be amended, as appropriate after consultation with other departments and agencies, through periodic republication by the Secretary, HHS, in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E>. A copy of the list is available from the Office for Human Research Protections, HHS, or any successor office.</P>
        <P>(b) An IRB may use the expedited review procedure to review either or both of the following:</P>
        <P>(1) Some or all of the research appearing on the list and found by the reviewer(s) to involve no more than minimal risk,</P>
        <P>(2) Minor changes in previously approved research during the period (of one year or less) for which approval is authorized.</P>

        <FP>Under an expedited review procedure, the review may be carried out by the IRB chairperson or by one or more experienced reviewers designated by the chairperson from among members of the IRB. In reviewing the research, the reviewers may exercise all of the authorities of the IRB except that the reviewers may not disapprove the research. A research activity may be disapproved only after review in accordance with the non-expedited procedure set forth in § 46.108(b).<PRTPAGE P="122"/>
        </FP>
        <P>(c) Each IRB which uses an expedited review procedure shall adopt a method for keeping all members advised of research proposals which have been approved under the procedure.</P>
        <P>(d) The department or agency head may restrict, suspend, terminate, or choose not to authorize an institution's or IRB's use of the expedited review procedure.</P>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.111</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Criteria for IRB approval of research.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) In order to approve research covered by this policy the IRB shall determine that all of the following requirements are satisfied:</P>
        <P>(1) Risks to subjects are minimized: (i) By using procedures which are consistent with sound research design and which do not unnecessarily expose subjects to risk, and (ii) whenever appropriate, by using procedures already being performed on the subjects for diagnostic or treatment purposes.</P>
        <P>(2) Risks to subjects are reasonable in relation to anticipated benefits, if any, to subjects, and the importance of the knowledge that may reasonably be expected to result. In evaluating risks and benefits, the IRB should consider only those risks and benefits that may result from the research (as distinguished from risks and benefits of therapies subjects would receive even if not participating in the research). The IRB should not consider possible long-range effects of applying knowledge gained in the research (for example, the possible effects of the research on public policy) as among those research risks that fall within the purview of its responsibility.</P>
        <P>(3) Selection of subjects is equitable. In making this assessment the IRB should take into account the purposes of the research and the setting in which the research will be conducted and should be particularly cognizant of the special problems of research involving vulnerable populations, such as children, prisoners, pregnant women, mentally disabled persons, or economically or educationally disadvantaged persons.</P>
        <P>(4) Informed consent will be sought from each prospective subject or the subject's legally authorized representative, in accordance with, and to the extent required by § 46.116.</P>
        <P>(5) Informed consent will be appropriately documented, in accordance with, and to the extent required by § 46.117.</P>
        <P>(6) When appropriate, the research plan makes adequate provision for monitoring the data collected to ensure the safety of subjects.</P>
        <P>(7) When appropriate, there are adequate provisions to protect the privacy of subjects and to maintain the confidentiality of data.</P>
        <P>(b) When some or all of the subjects are likely to be vulnerable to coercion or undue influence, such as children, prisoners, pregnant women, mentally disabled persons, or economically or educationally disadvantaged persons, additional safeguards have been included in the study to protect the rights and welfare of these subjects.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.112</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Review by institution.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Research covered by this policy that has been approved by an IRB may be subject to further appropriate review and approval or disapproval by officials of the institution. However, those officials may not approve the research if it has not been approved by an IRB.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.113</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Suspension or termination of IRB approval of research.</SUBJECT>
        <P>An IRB shall have authority to suspend or terminate approval of research that is not being conducted in accordance with the IRB's requirements or that has been associated with unexpected serious harm to subjects. Any suspension or termination of approval shall include a statement of the reasons for the IRB's action and shall be reported promptly to the investigator, appropriate institutional officials, and the department or agency head.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.114</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Cooperative research.</SUBJECT>

        <P>Cooperative research projects are those projects covered by this policy <PRTPAGE P="123"/>which involve more than one institution. In the conduct of cooperative research projects, each institution is responsible for safeguarding the rights and welfare of human subjects and for complying with this policy. With the approval of the department or agency head, an institution participating in a cooperative project may enter into a joint review arrangement, rely upon the review of another qualified IRB, or make similar arrangements for avoiding duplication of effort.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.115</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB records.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) An institution, or when appropriate an IRB, shall prepare and maintain adequate documentation of IRB activities, including the following:</P>
        <P>(1) Copies of all research proposals reviewed, scientific evaluations, if any, that accompany the proposals, approved sample consent documents, progress reports submitted by investigators, and reports of injuries to subjects.</P>
        <P>(2) Minutes of IRB meetings which shall be in sufficient detail to show attendance at the meetings; actions taken by the IRB; the vote on these actions including the number of members voting for, against, and abstaining; the basis for requiring changes in or disapproving research; and a written summary of the discussion of controverted issues and their resolution.</P>
        <P>(3) Records of continuing review activities.</P>
        <P>(4) Copies of all correspondence between the IRB and the investigators.</P>
        <P>(5) A list of IRB members in the same detail as described is § 46.103(b)(3).</P>
        <P>(6) Written procedures for the IRB in the same detail as described in § 46.103(b)(4) and § 46.103(b)(5).</P>
        <P>(7) Statements of significant new findings provided to subjects, as required by § 46.116(b)(5).</P>
        <P>(b) The records required by this policy shall be retained for at least 3 years, and records relating to research which is conducted shall be retained for at least 3 years after completion of the research. All records shall be accessible for inspection and copying by authorized representatives of the department or agency at reasonable times and in a reasonable manner.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.116</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>General requirements for informed consent.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Except as provided elsewhere in this policy, no investigator may involve a human being as a subject in research covered by this policy unless the investigator has obtained the legally effective informed consent of the subject or the subject's legally authorized representative. An investigator shall seek such consent only under circumstances that provide the prospective subject or the representative sufficient opportunity to consider whether or not to participate and that minimize the possibility of coercion or undue influence. The information that is given to the subject or the representative shall be in language understandable to the subject or the representative. No informed consent, whether oral or written, may include any exculpatory language through which the subject or the representative is made to waive or appear to waive any of the subject's legal rights, or releases or appears to release the investigator, the sponsor, the institution or its agents from liability for negligence.</P>
        <P>(a) Basic elements of informed consent. Except as provided in paragraph (c) or (d) of this section, in seeking informed consent the following information shall be provided to each subject:</P>
        <P>(1) A statement that the study involves research, an explanation of the purposes of the research and the expected duration of the subject's participation, a description of the procedures to be followed, and identification of any procedures which are experimental;</P>
        <P>(2) A description of any reasonably foreseeable risks or discomforts to the subject;</P>
        <P>(3) A description of any benefits to the subject or to others which may reasonably be expected from the research;</P>

        <P>(4) A disclosure of appropriate alternative procedures or courses of treatment, if any, that might be advantageous to the subject;<PRTPAGE P="124"/>
        </P>
        <P>(5) A statement describing the extent, if any, to which confidentiality of records identifying the subject will be maintained;</P>
        <P>(6) For research involving more than minimal risk, an explanation as to whether any compensation and an explanation as to whether any medical treatments are available if injury occurs and, if so, what they consist of, or where further information may be obtained;</P>
        <P>(7) An explanation of whom to contact for answers to pertinent questions about the research and research subjects' rights, and whom to contact in the event of a research-related injury to the subject; and</P>
        <P>(8) A statement that participation is voluntary, refusal to participate will involve no penalty or loss of benefits to which the subject is otherwise entitled, and the subject may discontinue participation at any time without penalty or loss of benefits to which the subject is otherwise entitled.</P>
        <P>(b) Additional elements of informed consent. When appropriate, one or more of the following elements of information shall also be provided to each subject:</P>
        <P>(1) A statement that the particular treatment or procedure may involve risks to the subject (or to the embryo or fetus, if the subject is or may become pregnant) which are currently unforeseeable;</P>
        <P>(2) Anticipated circumstances under which the subject's participation may be terminated by the investigator without regard to the subject's consent;</P>
        <P>(3) Any additional costs to the subject that may result from participation in the research;</P>
        <P>(4) The consequences of a subject's decision to withdraw from the research and procedures for orderly termination of participation by the subject;</P>
        <P>(5) A statement that significant new findings developed during the course of the research which may relate to the subject's willingness to continue participation will be provided to the subject; and</P>
        <P>(6) The approximate number of subjects involved in the study.</P>
        <P>(c) An IRB may approve a consent procedure which does not include, or which alters, some or all of the elements of informed consent set forth above, or waive the requirement to obtain informed consent provided the IRB finds and documents that:</P>
        <P>(1) The research or demonstration project is to be conducted by or subject to the approval of state or local government officials and is designed to study, evaluate, or otherwise examine: (i) Public benefit of service programs; (ii) procedures for obtaining benefits or services under those programs; (iii) possible changes in or alternatives to those programs or procedures; or (iv) possible changes in methods or levels of payment for benefits or services under those programs; and</P>
        <P>(2) The research could not practicably be carried out without the waiver or alteration.</P>
        <P>(d) An IRB may approve a consent procedure which does not include, or which alters, some or all of the elements of informed consent set forth in this section, or waive the requirements to obtain informed consent provided the IRB finds and documents that:</P>
        <P>(1) The research involves no more than minimal risk to the subjects;</P>
        <P>(2) The waiver or alteration will not adversely affect the rights and welfare of the subjects;</P>
        <P>(3) The research could not practicably be carried out without the waiver or alteration; and</P>
        <P>(4) Whenever appropriate, the subjects will be provided with additional pertinent information after participation.</P>
        <P>(e) The informed consent requirements in this policy are not intended to preempt any applicable federal, state, or local laws which require additional information to be disclosed in order for informed consent to be legally effective.</P>
        <P>(f) Nothing in this policy is intended to limit the authority of a physician to provide emergency medical care, to the extent the physician is permitted to do so under applicable federal, state, or local law.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="125"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.117</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Documentation of informed consent.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Except as provided in paragraph (c) of this section, informed consent shall be documented by the use of a written consent form approved by the IRB and signed by the subject or the subject's legally authorized representative. A copy shall be given to the person signing the form.</P>
        <P>(b) Except as provided in paragraph (c) of this section, the consent form may be either of the following:</P>
        <P>(1) A written consent document that embodies the elements of informed consent required by § 46.116. This form may be read to the subject or the subject's legally authorized representative, but in any event, the investigator shall give either the subject or the representative adequate opportunity to read it before it is signed; or</P>
        <P>(2) A short form written consent document stating that the elements of informed consent required by § 46.116 have been presented orally to the subject or the subject's legally authorized representative. When this method is used, there shall be a witness to the oral presentation. Also, the IRB shall approve a written summary of what is to be said to the subject or the representative. Only the short form itself is to be signed by the subject or the representative. However, the witness shall sign both the short form and a copy of the summary, and the person actually obtaining consent shall sign a copy of the summary. A copy of the summary shall be given to the subject or the representative, in addition to a copy of the short form.</P>
        <P>(c) An IRB may waive the requirement for the investigator to obtain a signed consent form for some or all subjects if it finds either:</P>
        <P>(1) That the only record linking the subject and the research would be the consent document and the principal risk would be potential harm resulting from a breach of confidentiality. Each subject will be asked whether the subject wants documentation linking the subject with the research, and the subject's wishes will govern; or</P>
        <P>(2) That the research presents no more than minimal risk of harm to subjects and involves no procedures for which written consent is normally required outside of the research context.</P>
        <P>In cases in which the documentation requirement is waived, the IRB may require the investigator to provide subjects with a written statement regarding the research.</P>
        <APPRO>(Approved by the Office of Management and Budget under Control Number 0990-0260)</APPRO>
        <CITA>[56 FR 28012, 28022, June 18, 1991, as amended at 70 FR 36328, June 23, 2005]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.118</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applications and proposals lacking definite plans for involvement of human subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Certain types of applications for grants, cooperative agreements, or contracts are submitted to departments or agencies with the knowledge that subjects may be involved within the period of support, but definite plans would not normally be set forth in the application or proposal. These include activities such as institutional type grants when selection of specific projects is the institution's responsibility; research training grants in which the activities involving subjects remain to be selected; and projects in which human subjects' involvement will depend upon completion of instruments, prior animal studies, or purification of compounds. These applications need not be reviewed by an IRB before an award may be made. However, except for research exempted or waived under § 46.101 (b) or (i), no human subjects may be involved in any project supported by these awards until the project has been reviewed and approved by the IRB, as provided in this policy, and certification submitted, by the institution, to the department or agency.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.119</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research undertaken without the intention of involving human subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In the event research is undertaken without the intention of involving human subjects, but it is later proposed to involve human subjects in the research, the research shall first be reviewed and approved by an IRB, as provided in this policy, a certification submitted, by the institution, to the department or agency, and final approval given to the proposed change by the department or agency.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="126"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.120</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Evaluation and disposition of applications and proposals for research to be conducted or supported by a Federal Department or Agency.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The department or agency head will evaluate all applications and proposals involving human subjects submitted to the department or agency through such officers and employees of the department or agency and such experts and consultants as the department or agency head determines to be appropriate. This evaluation will take into consideration the risks to the subjects, the adequacy of protection against these risks, the potential benefits of the research to the subjects and others, and the importance of the knowledge gained or to be gained.</P>
        <P>(b) On the basis of this evaluation, the department or agency head may approve or disapprove the application or proposal, or enter into negotiations to develop an approvable one.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.121</SECTNO>
        <RESERVED>[Reserved]</RESERVED>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.122</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Use of Federal funds.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Federal funds administered by a department or agency may not be expended for research involving human subjects unless the requirements of this policy have been satisfied.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.123</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Early termination of research support: Evaluation of applications and proposals.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The department or agency head may require that department or agency support for any project be terminated or suspended in the manner prescribed in applicable program requirements, when the department or agency head finds an institution has materially failed to comply with the terms of this policy.</P>
        <P>(b) In making decisions about supporting or approving applications or proposals covered by this policy the department or agency head may take into account, in addition to all other eligibility requirements and program criteria, factors such as whether the applicant has been subject to a termination or suspension under paragarph (a) of this section and whether the applicant or the person or persons who would direct or has have directed the scientific and technical aspects of an activity has have, in the judgment of the department or agency head, materially failed to discharge responsibility for the protection of the rights and welfare of human subjects (whether or not the research was subject to federal regulation).</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.124</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Conditions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>With respect to any research project or any class of research projects the department or agency head may impose additional conditions prior to or at the time of approval when in the judgment of the department or agency head additional conditions are necessary for the protection of human subjects.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart B—Additional Protections for Pregnant Women, Human Fetuses and Neonates Involved in Research</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>66 FR 56778, Nov. 13, 2001, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.201</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what do these regulations apply?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Except as provided in paragraph (b) of this section, this subpart applies to all research involving pregnant women, human fetuses, neonates of uncertain viability, or nonviable neonates conducted or supported by the Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS). This includes all research conducted in DHHS facilities by any person and all research conducted in any facility by DHHS employees.</P>
        <P>(b) The exemptions at § 46.101(b)(1) through (6) are applicable to this subpart.</P>
        <P>(c) The provisions of § 46.101(c) through (i) are applicable to this subpart. Reference to State or local laws in this subpart and in § 46.101(f) is intended to include the laws of federally recognized American Indian and Alaska Native Tribal Governments.</P>
        <P>(d) The requirements of this subpart are in addition to those imposed under the other subparts of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.202</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>

        <P>The definitions in § 46.102 shall be applicable to this subpart as well. In addition, as used in this subpart:<PRTPAGE P="127"/>
        </P>
        <P>(a) Dead fetus means a fetus that exhibits neither heartbeat, spontaneous respiratory activity, spontaneous movement of voluntary muscles, nor pulsation of the umbilical cord.</P>
        <P>(b) Delivery means complete separation of the fetus from the woman by expulsion or extraction or any other means.</P>
        <P>(c) Fetus means the product of conception from implantation until delivery.</P>
        <P>(d) Neonate means a newborn.</P>
        <P>(e) Nonviable neonate means a neonate after delivery that, although living, is not viable.</P>
        <P>(f) Pregnancy encompasses the period of time from implantation until delivery. A woman shall be assumed to be pregnant if she exhibits any of the pertinent presumptive signs of pregnancy, such as missed menses, until the results of a pregnancy test are negative or until delivery.</P>
        <P>(g) Secretary means the Secretary of Health and Human Services and any other officer or employee of the Department of Health and Human Services to whom authority has been delegated.</P>

        <P>(h) Viable, as it pertains to the neonate, means being able, after delivery, to survive (given the benefit of available medical therapy) to the point of independently maintaining heartbeat and respiration. The Secretary may from time to time, taking into account medical advances, publish in the <E T="04">Federal Register</E> guidelines to assist in determining whether a neonate is viable for purposes of this subpart. If a neonate is viable then it may be included in research only to the extent permitted and in accordance with the requirements of subparts A and D of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.203</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Duties of IRBs in connection with research involving pregnant women, fetuses, and neonates.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In addition to other responsibilities assigned to IRBs under this part, each IRB shall review research covered by this subpart and approve only research which satisfies the conditions of all applicable sections of this subpart and the other subparts of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.204</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving pregnant women or fetuses.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Pregnant women or fetuses may be involved in research if all of the following conditions are met:</P>
        <P>(a) Where scientifically appropriate, preclinical studies, including studies on pregnant animals, and clinical studies, including studies on nonpregnant women, have been conducted and provide data for assessing potential risks to pregnant women and fetuses;</P>
        <P>(b) The risk to the fetus is caused solely by interventions or procedures that hold out the prospect of direct benefit for the woman or the fetus; or, if there is no such prospect of benefit, the risk to the fetus is not greater than minimal and the purpose of the research is the development of important biomedical knowledge which cannot be obtained by any other means;</P>
        <P>(c) Any risk is the least possible for achieving the objectives of the research;</P>
        <P>(d) If the research holds out the prospect of direct benefit to the pregnant woman, the prospect of a direct benefit both to the pregnant woman and the fetus, or no prospect of benefit for the woman nor the fetus when risk to the fetus is not greater than minimal and the purpose of the research is the development of important biomedical knowledge that cannot be obtained by any other means, her consent is obtained in accord with the informed consent provisions of subpart A of this part;</P>
        <P>(e) If the research holds out the prospect of direct benefit solely to the fetus then the consent of the pregnant woman and the father is obtained in accord with the informed consent provisions of subpart A of this part, except that the father's consent need not be obtained if he is unable to consent because of unavailability, incompetence, or temporary incapacity or the pregnancy resulted from rape or incest.</P>
        <P>(f) Each individual providing consent under paragraph (d) or (e) of this section is fully informed regarding the reasonably foreseeable impact of the research on the fetus or neonate;</P>

        <P>(g) For children as defined in § 46.402(a) who are pregnant, assent and permission are obtained in accord with the provisions of subpart D of this part;<PRTPAGE P="128"/>
        </P>
        <P>(h) No inducements, monetary or otherwise, will be offered to terminate a pregnancy;</P>
        <P>(i) Individuals engaged in the research will have no part in any decisions as to the timing, method, or procedures used to terminate a pregnancy; and</P>
        <P>(j) Individuals engaged in the research will have no part in determining the viability of a neonate.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.205</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving neonates.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Neonates of uncertain viability and nonviable neonates may be involved in research if all of the following conditions are met:</P>
        <P>(1) Where scientifically appropriate, preclinical and clinical studies have been conducted and provide data for assessing potential risks to neonates.</P>
        <P>(2) Each individual providing consent under paragraph (b)(2) or (c)(5) of this section is fully informed regarding the reasonably foreseeable impact of the research on the neonate.</P>
        <P>(3) Individuals engaged in the research will have no part in determining the viability of a neonate.</P>
        <P>(4) The requirements of paragraph (b) or (c) of this section have been met as applicable.</P>
        <P>(b) Neonates of uncertain viability. Until it has been ascertained whether or not a neonate is viable, a neonate may not be involved in research covered by this subpart unless the following additional conditions are met:</P>
        <P>(1) The IRB determines that:</P>
        <P>(i) The research holds out the prospect of enhancing the probability of survival of the neonate to the point of viability, and any risk is the least possible for achieving that objective, or</P>
        <P>(ii) The purpose of the research is the development of important biomedical knowledge which cannot be obtained by other means and there will be no added risk to the neonate resulting from the research; and</P>
        <P>(2) The legally effective informed consent of either parent of the neonate or, if neither parent is able to consent because of unavailability, incompetence, or temporary incapacity, the legally effective informed consent of either parent's legally authorized representative is obtained in accord with subpart A of this part, except that the consent of the father or his legally authorized representative need not be obtained if the pregnancy resulted from rape or incest.</P>
        <P>(c) Nonviable neonates. After delivery nonviable neonate may not be involved in research covered by this subpart unless all of the following additional conditions are met:</P>
        <P>(1) Vital functions of the neonate will not be artificially maintained;</P>
        <P>(2) The research will not terminate the heartbeat or respiration of the neonate;</P>
        <P>(3) There will be no added risk to the neonate resulting from the research;</P>
        <P>(4) The purpose of the research is the development of important biomedical knowledge that cannot be obtained by other means; and</P>
        <P>(5) The legally effective informed consent of both parents of the neonate is obtained in accord with subpart A of this part, except that the waiver and alteration provisions of § 46.116(c) and (d) do not apply. However, if either parent is unable to consent because of unavailability, incompetence, or temporary incapacity, the informed consent of one parent of a nonviable neonate will suffice to meet the requirements of this paragraph (c)(5), except that the consent of the father need not be obtained if the pregnancy resulted from rape or incest. The consent of a legally authorized representative of either or both of the parents of a nonviable neonate will not suffice to meet the requirements of this paragraph (c)(5).</P>
        <P>(d) Viable neonates. A neonate, after delivery, that has been determined to be viable may be included in research only to the extent permitted by and in accord with the requirements of subparts A and D of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.206</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving, after delivery, the placenta, the dead fetus or fetal material.</SUBJECT>

        <P>(a) Research involving, after delivery, the placenta; the dead fetus; macerated fetal material; or cells, tissue, or organs excised from a dead fetus, shall be conducted only in accord with any applicable Federal, State, or local laws and regulations regarding such activities.<PRTPAGE P="129"/>
        </P>
        <P>(b) If information associated with material described in paragraph (a) of this section is recorded for research purposes in a manner that living individuals can be identified, directly or through identifiers linked to those individuals, those individuals are research subjects and all pertinent subparts of this part are applicable.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.207</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not otherwise approvable which presents an opportunity to understand, prevent, or alleviate a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of pregnant women, fetuses, or neonates.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The Secretary will conduct or fund research that the IRB does not believe meets the requirements of § 46.204 or § 46.205 only if:</P>
        <P>(a) The IRB finds that the research presents a reasonable opportunity to further the understanding, prevention, or alleviation of a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of pregnant women, fetuses or neonates; and</P>

        <P>(b) The Secretary, after consultation with a panel of experts in pertinent disciplines (for example: science, medicine, ethics, law) and following opportunity for public review and comment, including a public meeting announced in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> has determined either:</P>
        <P>(1) That the research in fact satisfies the conditions of § 46.204, as applicable; or</P>
        <P>(2) The following:</P>
        <P>(i) The research presents a reasonable opportunity to further the understanding, prevention, or alleviation of a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of pregnant women, fetuses or neonates;</P>
        <P>(ii) The research will be conducted in accord with sound ethical principles; and</P>
        <P>(iii) Informed consent will be obtained in accord with the informed consent provisions of subpart A and other applicable subparts of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart C—Additional Protections Pertaining to Biomedical and Behavioral Research Involving Prisoners as Subjects</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>43 FR 53655, Nov. l6, l978, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.301</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Applicability.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) The regulations in this subpart are applicable to all biomedical and behavioral research conducted or supported by the Department of Health and Human Services involving prisoners as subjects.</P>
        <P>(b) Nothing in this subpart shall be construed as indicating that compliance with the procedures set forth herein will authorize research involving prisoners as subjects, to the extent such research is limited or barred by applicable State or local law.</P>
        <P>(c) The requirements of this subpart are in addition to those imposed under the other subparts of this part.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.302</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Purpose.</SUBJECT>
        <P>Inasmuch as prisoners may be under constraints because of their incarceration which could affect their ability to make a truly voluntary and uncoerced decision whether or not to participate as subjects in research, it is the purpose of this subpart to provide additional safeguards for the protection of prisoners involved in activities to which this subpart is applicable.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.303</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>As used in this subpart:</P>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Secretary</E> means the Secretary of Health and Human Services and any other officer or employee of the Department of Health and Human Services to whom authority has been delegated.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">DHHS</E> means the Department of Health and Human Services.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Prisoner</E> means any individual involuntarily confined or detained in a penal institution. The term is intended to encompass individuals sentenced to such an institution under a criminal or civil statute, individuals detained in other facilities by virtue of statutes or commitment procedures which provide alternatives to criminal prosecution or incarceration in a penal institution, and individuals detained pending arraignment, trial, or sentencing.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Minimal risk</E> is the probability and magnitude of physical or psychological harm that is normally encountered in the daily lives, or in the routine medical, dental, or psychological examination of healthy persons.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="130"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.304</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Composition of Institutional Review Boards where prisoners are involved.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In addition to satisfying the requirements in § 46.107 of this part, an Institutional Review Board, carrying out responsibilities under this part with respect to research covered by this subpart, shall also meet the following specific requirements:</P>
        <P>(a) A majority of the Board (exclusive of prisoner members) shall have no association with the prison(s) involved, apart from their membership on the Board.</P>
        <P>(b) At least one member of the Board shall be a prisoner, or a prisoner representative with appropriate background and experience to serve in that capacity, except that where a particular research project is reviewed by more than one Board only one Board need satisfy this requirement.</P>
        <CITA>[43 FR 53655, Nov. 16, 1978, as amended at 46 FR 8386, Jan. 26, 1981]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.305</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Additional duties of the Institutional Review Boards where prisoners are involved.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) In addition to all other responsibilities prescribed for Institutional Review Boards under this part, the Board shall review research covered by this subpart and approve such research only if it finds that:</P>
        <P>(1) The research under review represents one of the categories of research permissible under § 46.306(a)(2);</P>
        <P>(2) Any possible advantages accruing to the prisoner through his or her participation in the research, when compared to the general living conditions, medical care, quality of food, amenities and opportunity for earnings in the prison, are not of such a magnitude that his or her ability to weigh the risks of the research against the value of such advantages in the limited choice environment of the prison is impaired;</P>
        <P>(3) The risks involved in the research are commensurate with risks that would be accepted by nonprisoner volunteers;</P>
        <P>(4) Procedures for the selection of subjects within the prison are fair to all prisoners and immune from arbitrary intervention by prison authorities or prisoners. Unless the principal investigator provides to the Board justification in writing for following some other procedures, control subjects must be selected randomly from the group of available prisoners who meet the characteristics needed for that particular research project;</P>
        <P>(5) The information is presented in language which is understandable to the subject population;</P>
        <P>(6) Adequate assurance exists that parole boards will not take into account a prisoner's participation in the research in making decisions regarding parole, and each prisoner is clearly informed in advance that participation in the research will have no effect on his or her parole; and</P>
        <P>(7) Where the Board finds there may be a need for follow-up examination or care of participants after the end of their participation, adequate provision has been made for such examination or care, taking into account the varying lengths of individual prisoners' sentences, and for informing participants of this fact.</P>
        <P>(b) The Board shall carry out such other duties as may be assigned by the Secretary.</P>
        <P>(c) The institution shall certify to the Secretary, in such form and manner as the Secretary may require, that the duties of the Board under this section have been fulfilled.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.306</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Permitted research involving prisoners.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Biomedical or behavioral research conducted or supported by DHHS may involve prisoners as subjects only if:</P>
        <P>(1) The institution responsible for the conduct of the research has certified to the Secretary that the Institutional Review Board has approved the research under § 46.305 of this subpart; and</P>
        <P>(2) In the judgment of the Secretary the proposed research involves solely the following:</P>
        <P>(i) Study of the possible causes, effects, and processes of incarceration, and of criminal behavior, provided that the study presents no more than minimal risk and no more than inconvenience to the subjects;</P>

        <P>(ii) Study of prisons as institutional structures or of prisoners as incarcerated persons, provided that the study <PRTPAGE P="131"/>presents no more than minimal risk and no more than inconvenience to the subjects;</P>

        <P>(iii) Research on conditions particularly affecting prisoners as a class (for example, vaccine trials and other research on hepatitis which is much more prevalent in prisons than elsewhere; and research on social and psychological problems such as alcoholism, drug addiction and sexual assaults) provided that the study may proceed only after the Secretary has consulted with appropriate experts including experts in penology medicine and ethics, and published notice, in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> of his intent to approve such research; or</P>

        <P>(iv) Research on practices, both innovative and accepted, which have the intent and reasonable probability of improving the health or well-being of the subject. In cases in which those studies require the assignment of prisoners in a manner consistent with protocols approved by the IRB to control groups which may not benefit from the research, the study may proceed only after the Secretary has consulted with appropriate experts, including experts in penology medicine and ethics, and published notice, in the <E T="04">Federal Register,</E> of his intent to approve such research.</P>
        <P>(b) Except as provided in paragraph (a) of this section, biomedical or behavioral research conducted or supported by DHHS shall not involve prisoners as subjects.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
    <SUBPART>
      <HD SOURCE="HED">Subpart D—Additional Protections for Children Involved as Subjects in Research</HD>
      <SOURCE>
        <HD SOURCE="HED">Source:</HD>
        <P>48 FR 9818, Mar. 8, 1983, unless otherwise noted.</P>
      </SOURCE>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.401</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>To what do these regulations apply?</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) This subpart applies to all research involving children as subjects, conducted or supported by the Department of Health and Human Services.</P>
        <P>(1) This includes research conducted by Department employees, except that each head of an Operating Division of the Department may adopt such nonsubstantive, procedural modifications as may be appropriate from an administrative standpoint.</P>
        <P>(2) It also includes research conducted or supported by the Department of Health and Human Services outside the United States, but in appropriate circumstances, the Secretary may, under paragraph (e) of § 46.101 of Subpart A, waive the applicability of some or all of the requirements of these regulations for research of this type.</P>
        <P>(b) Exemptions at § 46.101(b)(1) and (b)(3) through (b)(6) are applicable to this subpart. The exemption at § 46.101(b)(2) regarding educational tests is also applicable to this subpart. However, the exemption at § 46.101(b)(2) for research involving survey or interview procedures or observations of public behavior does not apply to research covered by this subpart, except for research involving observation of public behavior when the investigator(s) do not participate in the activities being observed.</P>
        <P>(c) The exceptions, additions, and provisions for waiver as they appear in paragraphs (c) through (i) of § 46.101 of Subpart A are applicable to this subpart.</P>
        <CITA>[48 FR 9818, Mar. 8, 1983; 56 FR 28032, June 18, 1991; 56 FR 29757, June 28, 1991]</CITA>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.402</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Definitions.</SUBJECT>
        <P>The definitions in § 46.102 of Subpart A shall be applicable to this subpart as well. In addition, as used in this subpart:</P>
        <P>(a) <E T="03">Children</E> are persons who have not attained the legal age for consent to treatments or procedures involved in the research, under the applicable law of the jurisdiction in which the research will be conducted.</P>
        <P>(b) <E T="03">Assent</E> means a child's affirmative agreement to participate in research. Mere failure to object should not, absent affirmative agreement, be construed as assent.</P>
        <P>(c) <E T="03">Permission</E> means the agreement of parent(s) or guardian to the participation of their child or ward in research.</P>
        <P>(d) <E T="03">Parent</E> means a child's biological or adoptive parent.</P>
        <P>(e) <E T="03">Guardian</E> means an individual who is authorized under applicable State or local law to consent on behalf of a child to general medical care.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="132"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.403</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>IRB duties.</SUBJECT>
        <P>In addition to other responsibilities assigned to IRBs under this part, each IRB shall review research covered by this subpart and approve only research which satisfies the conditions of all applicable sections of this subpart.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.404</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not involving greater than minimal risk.</SUBJECT>
        <P>HHS will conduct or fund research in which the IRB finds that no greater than minimal risk to children is presented, only if the IRB finds that adequate provisions are made for soliciting the assent of the children and the permission of their parents or guardians, as set forth in § 46.408.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.405</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving greater than minimal risk but presenting the prospect of direct benefit to the individual subjects.</SUBJECT>
        <P>HHS will conduct or fund research in which the IRB finds that more than minimal risk to children is presented by an intervention or procedure that holds out the prospect of direct benefit for the individual subject, or by a monitoring procedure that is likely to contribute to the subject's well-being, only if the IRB finds that:</P>
        <P>(a) The risk is justified by the anticipated benefit to the subjects;</P>
        <P>(b) The relation of the anticipated benefit to the risk is at least as favorable to the subjects as that presented by available alternative approaches; and</P>
        <P>(c) Adequate provisions are made for soliciting the assent of the children and permission of their parents or guardians, as set forth in § 46.408.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.406</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research involving greater than minimal risk and no prospect of direct benefit to individual subjects, but likely to yield generalizable knowledge about the subject's disorder or condition.</SUBJECT>
        <P>HHS will conduct or fund research in which the IRB finds that more than minimal risk to children is presented by an intervention or procedure that does not hold out the prospect of direct benefit for the individual subject, or by a monitoring procedure which is not likely to contribute to the well-being of the subject, only if the IRB finds that:</P>
        <P>(a) The risk represents a minor increase over minimal risk;</P>
        <P>(b) The intervention or procedure presents experiences to subjects that are reasonably commensurate with those inherent in their actual or expected medical, dental, psychological, social, or educational situations;</P>
        <P>(c) The intervention or procedure is likely to yield generalizable knowledge about the subjects' disorder or condition which is of vital importance for the understanding or amelioration of the subjects' disorder or condition; and</P>
        <P>(d) Adequate provisions are made for soliciting assent of the children and permission of their parents or guardians, as set forth in § 46.408.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.407</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Research not otherwise approvable which presents an opportunity to understand, prevent, or alleviate a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of children.</SUBJECT>
        <P>HHS will conduct or fund research that the IRB does not believe meets the requirements of § 46.404, § 46.405, or § 46.406 only if:</P>
        <P>(a) The IRB finds that the research presents a reasonable opportunity to further the understanding, prevention, or alleviation of a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of children; and</P>
        <P>(b) The Secretary, after consultation with a panel of experts in pertinent disciplines (for example: science, medicine, education, ethics, law) and following opportunity for public review and comment, has determined either:</P>
        <P>(1) That the research in fact satisfies the conditions of § 46.404, § 46.405, or § 46.406, as applicable, or</P>
        <P>(2) The following:</P>
        <P>(i) The research presents a reasonable opportunity to further the understanding, prevention, or alleviation of a serious problem affecting the health or welfare of children;</P>
        <P>(ii) The research will be conducted in accordance with sound ethical principles;</P>
        <P>(iii) Adequate provisions are made for soliciting the assent of children and the permission of their parents or guardians, as set forth in § 46.408.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <PRTPAGE P="133"/>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.408</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Requirements for permission by parents or guardians and for assent by children.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) In addition to the determinations required under other applicable sections of this subpart, the IRB shall determine that adequate provisions are made for soliciting the assent of the children, when in the judgment of the IRB the children are capable of providing assent. In determining whether children are capable of assenting, the IRB shall take into account the ages, maturity, and psychological state of the children involved. This judgment may be made for all children to be involved in research under a particular protocol, or for each child, as the IRB deems appropriate. If the IRB determines that the capability of some or all of the children is so limited that they cannot reasonably be consulted or that the intervention or procedure involved in the research holds out a prospect of direct benefit that is important to the health or well-being of the children and is available only in the context of the research, the assent of the children is not a necessary condition for proceeding with the research. Even where the IRB determines that the subjects are capable of assenting, the IRB may still waive the assent requirement under circumstances in which consent may be waived in accord with § 46.116 of Subpart A.</P>
        <P>(b) In addition to the determinations required under other applicable sections of this subpart, the IRB shall determine, in accordance with and to the extent that consent is required by § 46.116 of Subpart A, that adequate provisions are made for soliciting the permission of each child's parents or guardian. Where parental permission is to be obtained, the IRB may find that the permission of one parent is sufficient for research to be conducted under § 46.404 or § 46.405. Where research is covered by §§ 46.406 and 46.407 and permission is to be obtained from parents, both parents must give their permission unless one parent is deceased, unknown, incompetent, or not reasonably available, or when only one parent has legal responsibility for the care and custody of the child.</P>
        <P>(c) In addition to the provisions for waiver contained in § 46.116 of Subpart A, if the IRB determines that a research protocol is designed for conditions or for a subject population for which parental or guardian permission is not a reasonable requirement to protect the subjects (for example, neglected or abused children), it may waive the consent requirements in Subpart A of this part and paragraph (b) of this section, provided an appropriate mechanism for protecting the children who will participate as subjects in the research is substituted, and provided further that the waiver is not inconsistent with Federal, state or local law. The choice of an appropriate mechanism would depend upon the nature and purpose of the activities described in the protocol, the risk and anticipated benefit to the research subjects, and their age, maturity, status, and condition.</P>
        <P>(d) Permission by parents or guardians shall be documented in accordance with and to the extent required by § 46.117 of Subpart A.</P>
        <P>(e) When the IRB determines that assent is required, it shall also determine whether and how assent must be documented.</P>
      </SECTION>
      <SECTION>
        <SECTNO>§ 46.409</SECTNO>
        <SUBJECT>Wards.</SUBJECT>
        <P>(a) Children who are wards of the state or any other agency, institution, or entity can be included in research approved under § 46.406 or § 46.407 only if such research is:</P>
        <P>(1) Related to their status as wards; or</P>
        <P>(2) Conducted in schools, camps, hospitals, institutions, or similar settings in which the majority of children involved as subjects are not wards.</P>

        <P>(b) If the research is approved under paragraph (a) of this section, the IRB shall require appointment of an advocate for each child who is a ward, in addition to any other individual acting on behalf of the child as guardian or in loco parentis. One individual may serve as advocate for more than one child. The advocate shall be an individual who has the background and experience to act in, and agrees to act in, the best interests of the child for the duration of the child's participation in the research and who is not associated in any way (except in the role as advocate or member of the IRB) with the research, <PRTPAGE P="134"/>the investigator(s), or the guardian organization.</P>
      </SECTION>
    </SUBPART>
  </PART>
</CFRGRANULE>
